<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached in the cathedral church of Bristol, June xxi, MDCLXXXV before his grace Henry, Duke of Beavfort, His Majesties lord lieutenant for that city and county / by Ric. Thompson ...</title>
            <author>Thompson, Richard, 1647 or 8-1685.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1685</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 51 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62420</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T1007</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R8948</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11806516</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11806516</idno>
            <idno type="VID">49456</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62420)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 49456)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 552:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached in the cathedral church of Bristol, June xxi, MDCLXXXV before his grace Henry, Duke of Beavfort, His Majesties lord lieutenant for that city and county / by Ric. Thompson ...</title>
                  <author>Thompson, Richard, 1647 or 8-1685.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 26 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Luke Meredith ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1685.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Titus III, 1 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Duty --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons --  England --  17th century</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:49456:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49456:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached in the <hi>Cathedral Church</hi> OF BRISTOL, <hi>JUNE</hi> xxi. MDCLXXXV. Before His GRACE HENRY DUKE of <hi>BEA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>FORT,</hi> His MAJESTIE's Lord Lieutenant for that City and County.</p>
            <p>By <hi>RIC. THOMPSON</hi> D. D. Dean of <hi>Briſtol,</hi> and Chaplain in Ordinary to his late Majeſty.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>Luke Meredith,</hi> at the <hi>King's Head</hi> at the Weſt End of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard, 1685.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:49456:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49456:2"/>
            <head>To His Grace HENRY Duke of <hi>BEA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>FORT,</hi> Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs and Earl of <hi>Worcester,</hi> Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron <hi>Herbert</hi> of <hi>Chepſtow, Ragland,</hi> and <hi>Gower;</hi> Lord Preſident and Lord Lieutenant of <hi>Wales,</hi> and the <hi>Marches;</hi> Lord Lieutenant of the Counties of <hi>Glouceſter, Hereford,</hi> and <hi>Monmouth,</hi> and of the City and County of <hi>Briſtol;</hi> Lord Warden of His Majeſty's Foreſt of <hi>Dean,</hi> and Conſtable of the Caſtle of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Bria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vells,</hi> Knight of the moſt Noble <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> of the <hi>Garter,</hi> Gentleman of His Majeſty's Bed-Chamber, and one of His Majeſty's moſt Honourable Privy Council.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>May it pleaſe Your GRACE,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I <hi>Was far from making the ſame</hi> Eſtimate <hi>of this</hi> Diſcourſe <hi>which
<pb facs="tcp:49456:3"/> was put upon it by the</hi> Generality <hi>of Your</hi> Grace's Souldiers, <hi>who heard it preach'd. But ſince Your</hi> Grace <hi>hath had the</hi> Charity <hi>to think it worthy</hi> Theirs <hi>and other Peoples</hi> Reading, <hi>I am reſolved not to</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute <hi>Your</hi> Grace's Great Judgment: <hi>and ſo, do most readily</hi> ſubmit <hi>it to the</hi> Preſs; <hi>regardleſs of</hi> other <hi>mens</hi> Cenſures, <hi>whilſt Your</hi> Grace <hi>is plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to look on it as a</hi> Dutiful <hi>and</hi> well-meant <hi>Performance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Henceforward if any ask, What is in this</hi> Diſcourſe <hi>that ſhould move Your</hi> Grace <hi>to</hi> Order <hi>its being thus</hi> publick? <hi>I anſwer, It was</hi> deſign'd to promote Loyalty; <hi>the ſame</hi> Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty <hi>which now ſtands the</hi> Top <hi>and</hi> Comble <hi>of Your</hi> Grace's <hi>moſt</hi> Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious Titles and Characters, <hi>which render'd You</hi> all along <hi>a</hi> Great Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourite
<pb facs="tcp:49456:3"/> 
               <hi>of our late</hi> deceaſed <hi>Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign, and makes You</hi> moſt Dear <hi>unto his</hi> preſent Majeſty; <hi>which</hi> prevail'd <hi>with Your</hi> Grace <hi>in the</hi> very worſt <hi>of Times to</hi> aſſert <hi>his</hi> Majeſtie's Intereſts <hi>in</hi> Contempt <hi>of</hi> all <hi>Your</hi> Own, <hi>in</hi> defiance <hi>of the</hi> Excluding Bill, <hi>and all the</hi> Trayte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Votes <hi>and</hi> Deſigns <hi>of the</hi> Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſociated Commoners <hi>who promoted it. In ſhort, which brought Your</hi> Grace <hi>now down to</hi> Briſtol, <hi>by Your</hi> Vigilance <hi>and</hi> Reſolution <hi>to ſecure this</hi> City <hi>for his</hi> Majeſtie's <hi>Service, at a</hi> Time, <hi>when the</hi> Mock-King <hi>of</hi> Lyme <hi>had aſſured his</hi> Adherents, <hi>That this City</hi> was moſt certainly his own.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But Your</hi> Grace <hi>hath ſo</hi> effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally <hi>ſuceeded in Your <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndertaking, that the</hi> Daring Rebels <hi>had only ſo
<pb facs="tcp:49456:4"/> much</hi> Courage <hi>as to look upon the City at</hi> four Miles <hi>diſtance, and</hi> wiſh <hi>it</hi> theirs. <hi>The only</hi> Aſſault <hi>which they made upon Your</hi> Grace <hi>was a</hi> Volly <hi>of</hi> Lyes; <hi>(For having ſcarce</hi> laid <hi>it, they</hi> raiſed <hi>their</hi> Siege, <hi>with many bitter</hi> Curſings <hi>and</hi> Execrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons <hi>of Your</hi> Wiſe Conduct, <hi>at Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night</hi> cowardly <hi>running away.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>No wonder then that All</hi> honeſt <hi>and</hi> Loyal <hi>hearts within this</hi> City <hi>are now</hi> bleſſing <hi>God for Your</hi> Grace, <hi>and</hi> celebrating <hi>Your</hi> deſerved <hi>Prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, as the only</hi> viſible Means <hi>under Him, that hath</hi> ſecur'd <hi>to them their</hi> Eſtates, <hi>their</hi> Liberties, <hi>and their</hi> very Lives.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>As for my ſelf, the remembrance of my own</hi> Eſcape <hi>ſhall always live</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:49456:4"/> freſh <hi>in my mind, and I ſhall not fail to</hi> owne <hi>it to Your</hi> Grace <hi>upon all</hi> Occaſions, <hi>as becometh,</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>May it pleaſe Your Grace, <hi>Your Grace's moſt Humble, and moſt obliged Servant,</hi> Richard Thompſon.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:49456:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:49456:5"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>TITUS iii. v. 1.</bibl>
               <q>Put them in mind to be ſubject to Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipalities and Powers, to obey Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, and to be ready to every Good Work.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THESE Words are <hi>part</hi> of thoſe <hi>Inſtructions</hi> which St. <hi>Paul</hi> gave to <hi>Titus,</hi> touching thoſe <hi>Matters</hi> of <hi>Doctrine,</hi> which he would have him <hi>vigorouſly</hi> to inſiſt on, in his <hi>Courſe</hi> of <hi>Preaching</hi> among the people of <hi>Crete:</hi> They enjoin a <hi>peaceable</hi> and <hi>ſubmiſſive</hi> behavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our in all <hi>Chriſtians</hi> towards the <hi>Government,</hi> under which they live. Government being ſo <hi>great</hi> a <hi>Bleſſing</hi> to <hi>Mankind,</hi> that without it the <hi>World</hi> would be no <hi>better</hi> than a <hi>ſavage</hi> Wilderneſs, and an Habitation of <hi>Wolves</hi> and <hi>Tygers</hi> in <hi>hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane ſhape,</hi> rending and devouring one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>Wherefore <hi>Chriſt,</hi> when he came into the <hi>World,</hi> though he reſolved to ſet up a <hi>New</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:49456:6"/> in it, and knew that the <hi>preſent Powers</hi> would <hi>Oppoſe</hi> and <hi>Perſecute</hi> the <hi>Profeſſors</hi> of it to <hi>Death;</hi> yet did he take care withal, to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel his <hi>Diſciples</hi> and <hi>Followers</hi> patiently to <hi>ſuffer</hi> their utmoſt <hi>rage</hi> and <hi>cruelty,</hi> rather than there ſhould be any <hi>violent</hi> Alterations made in the <hi>Kingdoms</hi> of the <hi>Earth,</hi> upon the very ſcore of his <hi>Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He would not have Princes turn'd <hi>out</hi> of their <hi>Temporal</hi> Juriſdictions, nor the Sword <hi>wreſted</hi> out of their <hi>Hands,</hi> in order to the <hi>Eſtabliſhment</hi> of his <hi>Own</hi> Throne; neither would he, that his <hi>Kingdom</hi> ſhould go up with the <hi>Noiſes</hi> of <hi>Axes</hi> and <hi>Hammers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If the <hi>Rulers</hi> of the World would keep <hi>up</hi> their <hi>old</hi> Religion, and <hi>oppoſe</hi> his, he would not have <hi>Fire to come down from Heaven to conſume them,</hi> nor <hi>Fire</hi> from <hi>Hell</hi> to <hi>blow</hi> them <hi>up;</hi> but that all that were <hi>his</hi> Servants indeed, ſhould <hi>overcome</hi> with <hi>Patience</hi> and <hi>Meekneſs,</hi> and <hi>ſhine</hi> in the <hi>whiteneſs</hi> of <hi>Innocency,</hi> and not look <hi>dreadful</hi> with Garments <hi>roll'd</hi> in <hi>Blood:</hi> And therefore he hath given it in <hi>charge</hi> to all the <hi>Miniſters</hi> of his <hi>Goſpel,</hi> To put all the <hi>Profeſſors</hi> of his <hi>Religion</hi> in mind <hi>To be ſubject to Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>palities and Powers, to obey Magiſtrates, and to be ready to every Good Work.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In which words Two things are obſervable.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:49456:6"/>
            <p n="1">I. What the <hi>Duty</hi> of <hi>all</hi> Chriſtians is, who live under <hi>Government,</hi> viz. <hi>To be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="2">II. What the <hi>Duty</hi> of <hi>all</hi> the Miniſters of <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Goſpel is, <hi>viz. To put the people in mind to be ſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall only be able to ſpeak to the Firſt of theſe at this time, <hi>viz.</hi> The <hi>Duty</hi> that God hath bound upon <hi>all</hi> Chriſtians that live under <hi>Government,</hi> viz. <hi>To be ſubject to thoſe Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipalities and Powers under which they live.</hi> Where my work will be to ſhew Two things:</p>
            <p>I. Wherein the <hi>Practiſe</hi> of this <hi>Duty</hi> doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt. 2. The <hi>Extent</hi> of it.</p>
            <p>I. I ſhall ſhew wherein the <hi>Practiſe</hi> of this <hi>Duty</hi> of <hi>Subjection</hi> doth conſiſt.</p>
            <p>Now the Practiſe of this <hi>Duty</hi> of <hi>Subjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> conſiſts in <hi>Three</hi> things.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> In paying an <hi>Active Obedience</hi> to all our Prince's <hi>Juſt</hi> Commands.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> In <hi>ſuffering</hi> patiently, in caſe they ſhould <hi>oppreſs</hi> and <hi>puniſh</hi> us for not obſerving even their <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlawful</hi> Commands.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> In <hi>honoring</hi> the <hi>Perſons</hi> of the <hi>Princes</hi> under whom we live.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:49456:7"/>
            <p>Firſt, This <hi>Duty</hi> of <hi>Subjection,</hi> it requires we ſhould give an <hi>Active Obedience</hi> unto all our Prince's <hi>juſt</hi> Commands; <hi>i. e.</hi> We are to <hi>own</hi> their <hi>Authority</hi> in <hi>all</hi> things that are not <hi>ſinful</hi> for us to do. For in ſuch caſes, we may not ſatisfie our ſelves that we are <hi>ready</hi> to <hi>undergo</hi> the <hi>penalties</hi> of <hi>Laws.</hi> For, the <hi>Deſign</hi> of the <hi>Law,</hi> is to have Men <hi>Obey,</hi> not to have them <hi>Puniſhed.</hi> And Men ought in thoſe caſes <hi>to be ſubject, not only for Wrath, but alſo for Conſcience ſake:</hi> i. e. for the Lord <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s ſake, by whom our <hi>Conſciences</hi> are <hi>obliged.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is ſaid of <hi>Ariſtippus,</hi> That being asked what he had benefited by <hi>Philoſophy,</hi> he An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, <hi>To live uprightly and juſtly, although there were no Laws to compel, or Gods to puniſh him.</hi> And if an <hi>Heathen</hi> Man, acted by the <hi>meer</hi> Light of <hi>Nature,</hi> could do <hi>ſo much,</hi> much <hi>more</hi> ſhould <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Men do, conſidering that they live under a much <hi>higher,</hi> and a more <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi> and <hi>Advantageous</hi> Inſtitution. Chriſtian Men ſhould hold themſelves obliged to obſerve in their <hi>Actions,</hi> all the <hi>ends</hi> and <hi>deſigns</hi> of the <hi>Chriſtian Laws,</hi> and <hi>comply</hi> with them; and not think themſelves <hi>blameleſs,</hi> by coming <hi>up only</hi> to the <hi>Letter</hi> of them. For <hi>he</hi> whoſe <hi>Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> reaches no <hi>higher,</hi> obſerves the Law <hi>only for Wrath's ſake,</hi> and to ſave himſelf in an <hi>whole
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:49456:7"/> Skin.</hi> For, he would break the <hi>Letter</hi> as well as the <hi>Intention,</hi> if he could ſave himſelf <hi>harm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs.</hi> Such a Man doth <hi>not Obey for Conſcience ſake.</hi> And it is againſt all the Laws of Chriſt for Chriſtian Men to <hi>ſtudy</hi> only how to find out <hi>flawes</hi> in their Prince's Laws, and to ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie them only <hi>ſo</hi> far as thoſe words in <hi>rigor</hi> do require. But they ſhould hold themſelves obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to do all that in them lyeth to anſwer the <hi>full deſign</hi> and <hi>intention</hi> of them. Nor,</p>
            <p>Secondly, Doth our <hi>Duty</hi> require, That Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Men <hi>do</hi> the <hi>Commands</hi> of their <hi>Princes</hi> where they are <hi>Juſt,</hi> but alſo, That they ſhould <hi>ſuffer patiently</hi> under them, in caſe they ſhould <hi>oppreſs</hi> them; and they ſhould <hi>not reſiſt</hi> them, even although they <hi>puniſh</hi> them for <hi>not</hi> obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving their <hi>ſinful</hi> Commands. Indeed, in caſe their <hi>Commands</hi> are <hi>ſinful,</hi> they may <hi>ſuſpend</hi> their <hi>Active</hi> Obedience, but it muſt be <hi>certain</hi> that they are ſo, before they <hi>refuſe doing</hi> them. And they are <hi>then only ſo,</hi> when they <hi>require</hi> what <hi>God</hi> hath <hi>forbidden;</hi> as <hi>Nebuchadnezzor,</hi> when he required the <hi>Three Children to fall down and Worſhip the molten Image, that he had ſet up:</hi> or when they <hi>forbid</hi> what God hath <hi>required;</hi> as when <hi>Darius</hi> made a Law, <hi>That no Petition ſhould be made for Thirty Days together, unto any God, but to himſelf only.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:49456:8"/>
            <p>In which caſes <hi>we are to Obey God rather than Man.</hi> And then, indeed, it <hi>is thank-worthy, if a Man for Conſcience ſake towards God, endure Grief, ſuffering wrongfully. For even hereunto were we called; becauſe Chriſt alſo ſuffered for us, leaving us an Example that we ſhould follow his ſteps; who when he was reviled, reviled not again; when he ſuffer'd he threatned not, but committed himſelf to him that Judgeth Righteouſly.</hi> And yet,</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Whether the <hi>Obedience</hi> which Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Men pay to their <hi>Princes</hi> be <hi>Active,</hi> or <hi>Paſſive only,</hi> the <hi>Doctrine</hi> thereof doth moſt <hi>expreſsly</hi> require, That Chriſtians ſhould at <hi>all times</hi> and <hi>places,</hi> pay all <hi>due Honor</hi> to the <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of thoſe Sovereign Princes</hi> they live under: And that they ſhould treat them as having a <hi>Character</hi> of the <hi>Divinity</hi> ſet upon them; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe both their <hi>Perſons</hi> are <hi>Sacred,</hi> and the <hi>Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture</hi> it ſelf calls them <hi>Mortal Gods.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the <hi>Practice</hi> of this <hi>Duty</hi> will be <hi>indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferently</hi> well ſecured by obſerving theſe <hi>Nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives.</hi> Not to <hi>deprave</hi> the King's <hi>Government</hi> by loud <hi>Murmurings,</hi> by <hi>Libels,</hi> or other <hi>Sedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious</hi> Diſcourſes to <hi>alienate</hi> their Subjects <hi>hearts.</hi> For, as <hi>Subjects</hi> may not <hi>touch</hi> their Princes with a Violent <hi>Hand,</hi> ſo neither may they <hi>ſmite</hi> them with a Virulent <hi>Tongue.</hi> No, nor take <hi>delight</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:49456:8"/> in thoſe that Diſcourſe <hi>licenciouſly</hi> of <hi>Them,</hi> or their <hi>Affairs.</hi> To <hi>Honor</hi> the <hi>Perſon</hi> of the <hi>King</hi> obligeth us in <hi>no</hi> ſort to <hi>intrench</hi> upon his <hi>Royal Prerogative,</hi> nor to <hi>meddle</hi> in any thing that <hi>ſpeaks</hi> and <hi>conſtitutes</hi> him <hi>King;</hi> for theſe things are againſt his <hi>Honor</hi> and to the <hi>Diminution</hi> of his <hi>Crown.</hi> We muſt not ſo much as <hi>blazon</hi> his <hi>perſonal</hi> Infirmities, if we <hi>knew</hi> any that he had; and leaſt of all think that God hath put it in our power to ſay to his King, <hi>What doſt thou?</hi> But every one ought with profound <hi>Modeſty</hi> and <hi>Humility,</hi> to behave himſelf towards him, and to ſpeak <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>npleaſing Truths</hi> with greateſt <hi>Diſtance</hi> and <hi>Fear,</hi> when they are <hi>called</hi> to it: For <hi>Kings</hi> are <hi>not</hi> to be put to <hi>Shame.</hi> A Man muſt have a <hi>ſpecial</hi> and <hi>particular</hi> Commiſſion from <hi>God,</hi> by an <hi>extraordinary Revelation,</hi> before he can <hi>reprove</hi> a <hi>King.</hi> And <hi>ſuch</hi> Commiſſion <hi>no</hi> Man <hi>now</hi> can <hi>pretend</hi> unto.</p>
            <p>Indeed, in the <hi>Great</hi> Emergencies of the <hi>State,</hi> his Subjects, when <hi>he calls</hi> them together for <hi>that purpoſe,</hi> may with all <hi>Humility</hi> and <hi>Submiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> Addreſs to him, and in the <hi>meekeſt</hi> manner, repreſent what they take to be the <hi>evil</hi> Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences of things: But <hi>Remonſtrance,</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roar,</hi> and <hi>Tumult,</hi> are <hi>contrary</hi> to the <hi>Majeſty</hi> of a <hi>King,</hi> before whom all things <hi>ought</hi> to be <hi>calm</hi> and <hi>ſerene.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:49456:9"/>
            <p>And then as to the <hi>Affirmative</hi> part of this <hi>Duty</hi> of <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Obedience, to <hi>Honor</hi> the <hi>King,</hi> requires, That his Subjects ſhould not only <hi>ſpeak</hi> him <hi>fair,</hi> but <hi>do</hi> him <hi>good; bleſſing</hi> him, and <hi>praying</hi> for him, and <hi>rendring</hi> him <hi>Tribute.</hi> And even when they <hi>ſo</hi> do, if they would approve themſelves <hi>followers</hi> of Chriſt, and <hi>ſpeak</hi> in the <hi>language</hi> of the <hi>Holy Spirit,</hi> they may not ſay, they <hi>give</hi> the King <hi>this,</hi> or they <hi>give</hi> the King <hi>that:</hi> For, all that <hi>Subjects</hi> poſſeſs, is <hi>not</hi> their <hi>own; God</hi> hath <hi>one</hi> part due to him, and <hi>Caeſar</hi> hath <hi>another;</hi> and when they <hi>pay them,</hi> they do but <hi>render</hi> them their <hi>due.</hi> Nor, hath the <hi>King</hi> only a <hi>ſhare</hi> in their <hi>Eſtates,</hi> but their very <hi>Lives</hi> alſo are <hi>his.</hi> And ſo it is become their <hi>Duty</hi> to <hi>Fight</hi> for their Prince's <hi>Safety.</hi> And whoever doth not, upon <hi>Occaſion,</hi> Honor his Prince on <hi>this manner,</hi> he cannot be ſaid <hi>truly</hi> to <hi>fear</hi> God: For <hi>theſe</hi> are <hi>all</hi> alike <hi>branches</hi> of that <hi>Duty,</hi> which the <hi>Goſpel</hi> doth require, when it would have us <hi>Submit for Conſcience ſake, and for the Lord's ſake.</hi> I come now to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in the</p>
            <p>2d. Place, the <hi>Extent</hi> of this Obligation, both in reſpect of the <hi>Obedience it ſelf,</hi> as to the <hi>Matter</hi> of it, and of the <hi>Perſons,</hi> to <hi>whom,</hi> and the <hi>Time,</hi> how <hi>long</hi> this <hi>Precept</hi> is of <hi>force.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:49456:9"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> In reſpect of the <hi>Obedience it ſelf,</hi> it is ſo <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal,</hi> that it's not <hi>limited</hi> by the <hi>uſual</hi> limits of Mens <hi>Actions</hi> conſider'd in their <hi>ſingle capacity;</hi> not by <hi>Scandal;</hi> not by a <hi>Scrupulous Conſcience;</hi> no, nor by any <hi>Antecedent</hi> or <hi>Subſequent</hi> Vow.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Obedience</hi> and <hi>Subjection</hi> to the <hi>King,</hi> is not <hi>limited</hi> by Caſes of <hi>Scandal.</hi> Indeed, ſuch is the <hi>Strictneſs</hi> of the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, That it will not allow a Man in a <hi>ſingle capacity,</hi> to exerciſe his <hi>juſt</hi> Liberty in <hi>ſome</hi> Actions, whereby a <hi>weak</hi> Brother may be <hi>offended.</hi> And there may be an <hi>Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation</hi> of <hi>Charity</hi> that may bind this <hi>Duty</hi> upon a Man in his <hi>private</hi> Capacity. But if the <hi>Prince</hi> require <hi>ſuch</hi> a Man's <hi>Obedience,</hi> in <hi>ſuch</hi> or <hi>ſuch</hi> matters of Practice, as are <hi>lawful</hi> to be done, and other <hi>private</hi> perſons ſhall <hi>pretend</hi> themſelves <hi>offended</hi> thereby, and ſo incline to fall into Sin; Why, here, <hi>not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding</hi> this, we are <hi>bound</hi> to <hi>obey</hi> our <hi>Prince:</hi> Becauſe the <hi>avoiding Scandal,</hi> is but an <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Charity;</hi> but to <hi>Obey</hi> the <hi>Prince,</hi> is a <hi>matter</hi> of <hi>Juſtice;</hi> and we are always bound to pay <hi>Debts</hi> of <hi>Juſtice,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Debts</hi> of <hi>Charity.</hi> When we <hi>forbear</hi> an Act, <hi>only</hi> to avoid <hi>Scandal,</hi> we <hi>recede</hi> from
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:49456:10"/> our <hi>own Right,</hi> which we may do; but when the Prince <hi>enjoyns, even</hi> the Act, which we did before <hi>avoid,</hi> though we may give away our <hi>own</hi> Right, yet we have <hi>no power</hi> to give away our <hi>Prince's Right.</hi> Our <hi>Obedience</hi> is our Prince's <hi>Right,</hi> and if <hi>he</hi> will <hi>not</hi> remit it, we are <hi>bound</hi> to <hi>give</hi> it him. For, if in a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Common-wealth, men ſhould be <hi>free</hi> from <hi>Laws,</hi> by pleading, That they give <hi>offence;</hi> then <hi>every</hi> man that had no mind to <hi>Obey,</hi> would <hi>defend</hi> himſelf with this <hi>Plea;</hi> and ſo it would be left in the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>p-ſhot</hi> to the Peoples <hi>pleaſure,</hi> whether they would <hi>obey</hi> or <hi>no.</hi> And conſequently, <hi>none</hi> or very <hi>few</hi> Laws would be <hi>obſerved.</hi> And</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> As our <hi>Obedience</hi> unto our <hi>Prince</hi> is <hi>not</hi> limited by a Caſe of <hi>Scandal;</hi> ſo neither is it limited by a <hi>Scrupulous Conſcience.</hi> I mean, when a man, conſidering the <hi>Action</hi> that is <hi>commanded,</hi> doubts that it is <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlawful,</hi> but he is <hi>not</hi> certain; he hath ſome <hi>fear</hi> and <hi>diſtruſt</hi> upon him, but he is not fully perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; he <hi>cannot</hi> ſhew where in <hi>Scripture</hi> it is forbidden, but he <hi>only</hi> doubts. Now, though a man in his <hi>Private, ſingle</hi> Capacity, is in ſuch caſe bound to <hi>ſuſpend</hi> Acting, until his <hi>Conſcience</hi> be <hi>duly</hi> inform'd, (becauſe, <hi>what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:49456:10"/> is not of Faith, is Sin:) i. e.</hi> whatſoever is not done in ſuch caſe with a <hi>full</hi> perſwaſion, that it is <hi>lawful,</hi> is <hi>ſin:</hi> Yet, when the Prince requires <hi>Obedience,</hi> and we only <hi>doubt</hi> whether the <hi>Command</hi> be <hi>lawful,</hi> we are then <hi>bound</hi> to <hi>obey</hi> the <hi>Prince,</hi> becauſe he <hi>commands;</hi> and <hi>not</hi> to <hi>ſuſpend</hi> acting, becauſe we are <hi>ſcrupulous.</hi> For, it is <hi>certain,</hi> that we <hi>owe</hi> our <hi>Prince</hi> our <hi>Obedience;</hi> but it is <hi>not</hi> certain, that the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand</hi> is <hi>unlawful,</hi> and it is our <hi>Wiſdom</hi> and our <hi>Duty</hi> to adhere to the <hi>ſafer</hi> ſide. For, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, to <hi>refuſe</hi> the Prince, would be to <hi>run</hi> into a <hi>certain ſin,</hi> to <hi>avoid</hi> that which is <hi>uncertain.</hi> To <hi>obey</hi> the <hi>Prince</hi> in ſuch caſe is not for a man to act <hi>againſt</hi> his <hi>Conſcience.</hi> For, a <hi>doubting</hi> Conſcience, is <hi>not properly</hi> a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, becauſe it preſcribes <hi>no</hi> Rules, nor doth it, like a <hi>Judge,</hi> paſs a <hi>Sentence;</hi> neither can it <hi>excuſe</hi> or <hi>condemn.</hi> Nay,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly, Subjection</hi> to the Prince is <hi>due,</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can it be <hi>with-held</hi> from him; no, not by virtue of any <hi>Antecedent</hi> or <hi>Subſequent</hi> Vow.</p>
            <p>Indeed, it is written in the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Numbers</hi> 30. <hi>v.</hi> 2.</note> That <hi>if a man</hi> in a private Capacity <hi>vowed a Vow unto the Lord, or ſwore an Oath, he ſhould not break his Word, he ſhould do according to all that proceeded out of his Mouth. But if a
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:49456:11"/> Woman vow'd, and her Father heard it, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allow'd it in the day that he heard it,</hi> it is there alſo written, That <hi>not any of her Vow was to ſtand.</hi> The Reaſon is, becauſe <hi>ſhe was under ſubjection.</hi> And by as good <hi>Logick</hi> as any is, the ſame may be <hi>concluded</hi> concerning the <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation</hi> which lieth upon the <hi>people</hi> in <hi>reſpect</hi> of the <hi>Prince.</hi> The <hi>Sovereign Prince</hi> is the <hi>Father</hi> of his <hi>people;</hi> and therefore, if the <hi>people</hi> ſhould make a <hi>Vow,</hi> and enter into a <hi>Solemn League and Covenant,</hi> and the Prince ſhould by a <hi>publick Declaration diſallow</hi> it when he <hi>heard</hi> it, <hi>ſuch</hi> Vow of the people could have <hi>no binding</hi> power in it, and there lay <hi>no Obligation</hi> upon any ſuch Subjects, from any <hi>ſuch</hi> Vow, that they ſhould ſay, they <hi>cannot</hi> obey in <hi>this</hi> or in <hi>that</hi> thing, by reaſon of it: For, <hi>they are under Subjection.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This would hold, if the <hi>Vow</hi> or <hi>Oath</hi> were a thing <hi>lawful</hi> in it ſelf. But much <hi>more</hi> will it hold then, if the <hi>Oath</hi> is an <hi>unlawful</hi> Oath; as it <hi>needs</hi> muſt be, if people ſhall take an <hi>Oath,</hi> and <hi>enter</hi> into a <hi>Covenant</hi> to <hi>alter</hi> the <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,</hi> and <hi>depoſe</hi> their <hi>Governour,</hi> and eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially when they have <hi>before</hi> taken an <hi>Oath</hi> of <hi>Allegiance</hi> to their <hi>Governour,</hi> and an <hi>Oath</hi> to maintain his <hi>Government.</hi> Such an <hi>after-</hi>Oath
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:49456:11"/> of the <hi>Peoples,</hi> is <hi>unlawful</hi> in it ſelf; and therefore <hi>not</hi> binding; but they <hi>ought</hi> to <hi>obey</hi> the <hi>King</hi> for all <hi>that,</hi> in what <hi>lawful</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances ſoever he requireth their Obedience.</p>
            <p>This is the <hi>Extent</hi> of the Subject's Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, as to the <hi>matter</hi> of it. It now remains, That</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> We conſider the <hi>Extent</hi> of it, as to the <hi>Perſons</hi> to whom it muſt be paid; and that is <hi>General,</hi> to <hi>all Principalities and Powers,</hi> without <hi>any</hi> Limitation or Diſtinction. Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects are <hi>not only</hi> to obey them that are <hi>Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,</hi> and whom <hi>they</hi> acknowledge to be <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian;</hi> but even <hi>thoſe</hi> who are of a <hi>contrary</hi> Religion, and when they <hi>perſecute</hi> and <hi>oppoſe</hi> theirs. Subjects muſt <hi>ſubmit</hi> to <hi>thoſe</hi> Princes, if they be <hi>theirs.</hi> For, they are ſtill the <hi>Ordinances of God,</hi> whatever elſe they be. Thus, though the <hi>Principalities</hi> and <hi>Powers</hi> in St. <hi>Paul's</hi> time were <hi>Heathen,</hi> and <hi>Enemies to the Faith of Chriſt;</hi> and the Supream Power was then <hi>veſted</hi> in <hi>Nero,</hi> a very <hi>Cruel,</hi> and a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Debauch'd</hi> Prince; yet, for all <hi>this</hi> the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> were <hi>not</hi> to <hi>withdraw</hi> from <hi>him</hi> their Obedience. It was <hi>not permitted</hi> to any of his Subjects to <hi>ſay</hi> of him, that was their Prince, neither is it permitted to <hi>any</hi> Subjects
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:49456:12"/> whatever, to <hi>ſay</hi> of their Prince, That he is an <hi>Ill man,</hi> and a <hi>Tyrant,</hi> and an <hi>Enemy to Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> and a <hi>Hater</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> and <hi>Religion;</hi> and that therefore it being the <hi>Cauſe</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> they are <hi>bound</hi> to <hi>ſtand up,</hi> and <hi>ſhake off the Yoke,</hi> and come <hi>forth</hi> for the <hi>help of the Lord againſt the Mighty,</hi> i. e. <hi>to pull down Kings and Kingdoms:</hi> For, Chriſt hath <hi>commanded</hi> all Subjects to <hi>ſubmit themſelves,</hi> and <hi>render unto Caeſar the things that are Caeſar's;</hi> yea, although <hi>Caeſar</hi> ſhould take <hi>no</hi> care to <hi>render unto God the things that are God's.</hi> Nay, <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf, when upon an Occaſion the <hi>People would have taken him by Force, and made him a King, refuſed it,</hi> and choſe to <hi>pay Tribute to</hi> Caeſar; yea, though <hi>Caeſar</hi> held his power <hi>from</hi> and <hi>under</hi> him: And at another time he declared, <hi>That his Kingdom was not of this World,</hi> leaſt his Souldiers <hi>ſhould fight for him.</hi> From whence alſo it may be concluded, That ſince <hi>Chriſt's</hi> is a Kingdom of <hi>another</hi> Nature, his Souldiers are <hi>not</hi> to <hi>fight</hi> againſt their <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral</hi> Governour, even in <hi>Defence</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf.</p>
            <p>Since the <hi>Expulſion</hi> of the <hi>Canaanites</hi> by <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhua,</hi> there is <hi>no</hi> ſuch thing in <hi>Nature</hi> as an <hi>Holy War,</hi> though it be againſt <hi>Infidels,</hi> to <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:49456:12"/> Chriſt's</hi> Religion, and <hi>deſtroy</hi> theirs; and therefore, when the <hi>Popes</hi> of <hi>old</hi> excited <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Princes to the <hi>Expedition</hi> againſt the <hi>Turks</hi> for <hi>propagating</hi> the <hi>Goſpel;</hi> and when, in the late <hi>great</hi> Rebellion amongſt us, the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> conſpired againſt <hi>their Sovereign, King</hi> Charles the Firſt, <hi>under pretence of ſetting Jeſus Chriſt up upon his Throne,</hi> they both of them <hi>proſper'd</hi> accordingly. God, as he hath <hi>not</hi> allow'd any <hi>ſuch</hi> Wars in his <hi>Word,</hi> ſo he <hi>blaſted</hi> thoſe by his <hi>Providence,</hi> and that, he will ſtill blaſt all ſuch Deſigns unto the end of the World, I make not the <hi>leaſt</hi> Queſtion, when I conſider in the next place</p>
            <p>Thirdly, How <hi>long</hi> this <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Obedience is <hi>extended,</hi> in reſpect of <hi>Time.</hi> There are ſome Laws in Scripture that bind <hi>only</hi> for a Time, ſuch as are the <hi>Divine poſitive</hi> Laws, <hi>the Ceremonial of the</hi> Jews, and ſuch as the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> laid on the <hi>Gentiles</hi> that were <hi>expedient</hi> for the <hi>preſent</hi> Juncture and Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity; as, <hi>Not to eat things ſtrangled,</hi> and, <hi>To abſtain from blood,</hi> becauſe a <hi>charitable reſpect</hi> was expedient to be born to the <hi>Jews,</hi> until the <hi>Temple</hi> and <hi>Moſaick Inſtitutions</hi> ſhould be <hi>aboliſhed.</hi> Some there alſo that have boldly affirmed in print of late days, That
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:49456:13"/> the Law of <hi>ſubmitting to Governours, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally Heathen Ones, obliged no longer than the preſent Neceſſity, and the Churches Infancy.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Jon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon's <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian the Apoſtate.</hi>
                  </note> That it was to expire when Chriſtians had gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a ſtronger power to defend themſelves. That men are to follow Providence, as God puts them into a greater Capacity; and to uſe their pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and to underſtand all their former Obligations accordingly. That to ſubmit was only a proviſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Precept for the preſent time. That St.</hi> Paul <hi>laid this charge on the firſt Chriſtians, becauſe they durſt not by their Cenſures threaten and provoke the Heathen Emperours for fear of plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging the Church into a Sea of Perſecution; and that for this Cauſe alone, they did not exerciſe this Power.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is the Account alſo, which <hi>all</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels give of <hi>themſelves,</hi> and their <hi>reſiſting</hi> of <hi>Kings,</hi> when they are charged with walking <hi>contrary</hi> to the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of St. <hi>Peter</hi> and St. <hi>Paul.</hi> But now,</p>
            <p>Contrarily hereto, I ſhall ſhew that St. <hi>Paul &amp;c.</hi> intended <hi>this precept to hold in force for ever;</hi> not only from what hath already been obſerved out of the Life of our Saviour; but firſt of all, and <hi>chiefly,</hi> from the <hi>Reaſons</hi> given by St. <hi>Paul for Subjection;</hi> for thoſe Reaſons are <hi>permanent,</hi> and of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:49456:13"/> 
               <hi>Eternal Verity,</hi> ex. gr. <hi>That the Magiſtrate is the Miniſter of God; That all Powers are of God; That the Magiſtrate bears the Sword to execute Juſtice on thoſe that oppoſe him; That to reſiſt him, is to reſiſt the Ordinance of God; That we must be ſubject not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for Wrath, but alſo for Conſcience ſake;</hi> Theſe Reaſons are ſtill <hi>permanent,</hi> and of <hi>Eternal Verity:</hi> and therefore it may be inferr'd, That becauſe <hi>theſe</hi> which are the <hi>Foundation</hi> of the <hi>Command,</hi> continue <hi>always,</hi> therefore the <hi>Command</hi> will be <hi>al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways</hi> in <hi>force</hi> too, and ſo the Precept of <hi>Submiſſion</hi> was <hi>never</hi> intended for a <hi>mere proviſional</hi> Precept.</p>
            <p>Moreover, if <hi>this</hi> and <hi>other</hi> like <hi>Commands</hi> of God were to be thus interpreted as <hi>mere proviſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal</hi> Precepts, why then, by parity of Reaſon, the <hi>whole Scripture,</hi> as well as the <hi>Ceremonial Law,</hi> might be <hi>devoided</hi> of its <hi>Authority.</hi> And as the Caſe may be put, there may be <hi>more</hi> Reaſon, and it would be <hi>more</hi> agreeable to the <hi>ſence</hi> of the <hi>Scripture,</hi> to read the Text backward, <hi>viz.</hi> to <hi>put the people in mind not to be ſubject,</hi> or to be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject <hi>only</hi> for wrath, but <hi>not</hi> for Conſcience ſake, <hi>i. e.</hi> for <hi>fear</hi> of <hi>provoking</hi> the <hi>Powers</hi> to <hi>deſtroy</hi> us, but <hi>not</hi> out of any <hi>laſting</hi> obligation that Chriſt hath <hi>laid</hi> on us to <hi>Submit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. To ſay that theſe Precepts of Submiſſion were <hi>only proviſional,</hi> for the Infant-State of the Church, and not <hi>laſting Laws,</hi> would be to <hi>charge</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:49456:14"/> all the <hi>Ancient</hi> Profeſſors of <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> with the deepeſt <hi>Diſſimulation</hi> and <hi>Hypocriſie.</hi> It is to ſay, <hi>their</hi> Obedience to the <hi>Principalities</hi> of <hi>their Times,</hi> was but <hi>counterfeit, extorted,</hi> and <hi>wrung</hi> out of them by <hi>force:</hi> That all the <hi>Submiſſive</hi> Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies and Supplications of the <hi>Fathers,</hi> (the aſſured <hi>Teſtimonies</hi> of their <hi>Allegiance, Humility,</hi> and <hi>Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence)</hi> were only <hi>certain Forms</hi> of <hi>diſguiſed Speech,</hi> proceeding not <hi>freely</hi> from the Suggeſtions of <hi>Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity,</hi> but <hi>faintly</hi> and <hi>feignedly,</hi> and as proceeding from ſome violent <hi>Convulſion</hi> of Fear. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon it muſt <hi>inevitably</hi> follow, That all their <hi>Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> and <hi>Puniſhments,</hi> even unto <hi>Death,</hi> are <hi>wrongfully</hi> honour'd with the <hi>Title,</hi> and <hi>unjuſtly</hi> crown'd with the <hi>Crown</hi> of <hi>Martyrdom;</hi> becauſe their <hi>Patience,</hi> according to this Suppoſition, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded not from <hi>Choice</hi> and <hi>Election,</hi> but was <hi>vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently</hi> produced by <hi>force</hi> and <hi>Neceſſity:</hi> and ſo, whereas they did not <hi>mutinouſly</hi> and <hi>rebelliouſly riſe in Arms,</hi> to aſſwage the Flames of <hi>Tyrannical</hi> Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution, it was not for want of <hi>Will,</hi> but for lack of <hi>Power;</hi> of which <hi>falſe</hi> and <hi>forged</hi> Imputation the <hi>Fathers,</hi> both <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Latine,</hi> have cleared themſelves in their <hi>Writings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In them you will find that the <hi>Primitive</hi> Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians did not give place to the <hi>violence</hi> of <hi>Heathen</hi> Rulers by virtue of <hi>this</hi> Precept as a <hi>Proviſional</hi> Direction, accommodate to the <hi>Temper</hi> of <hi>thoſe</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:49456:14"/> Times; but as to a <hi>neceſſary</hi> and <hi>certain</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of God; and which was to be in <hi>force</hi> when the <hi>Church</hi> was grown <hi>up</hi> into a <hi>power</hi> and <hi>Multitude.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3. To ſay, That the Precepts of <hi>Obedience</hi> and <hi>Submiſſion</hi> were <hi>only Proviſional,</hi> &amp;c. is to teach a <hi>Doctrine</hi> that is moſt highly <hi>prejudicial</hi> or <hi>dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous</hi> to <hi>Chriſtians</hi> living under <hi>Heretical</hi> and <hi>Pagan</hi> Powers; <hi>ex. gr.</hi> make it but once known to the <hi>Emperour of the Turks,</hi> that the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> living <hi>within</hi> his <hi>Empire</hi> do take God's <hi>Commands</hi> of <hi>Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> to the <hi>Prince</hi> whom they count an <hi>Infidel,</hi> to be <hi>only proviſional Precepts</hi> for a <hi>time,</hi> and that they are only to wait for an <hi>Occaſion</hi> to <hi>ſhake off</hi> the Yoke of <hi>Turkiſh</hi> bondage; and doubtleſs, he will not ſpare with all ſpeed to root out the <hi>whole</hi> Stock of <hi>Chriſtians</hi> out of his <hi>Dominions:</hi> He would hold himſelf concern'd to do this for his <hi>own Safety.</hi> And then, this would be a <hi>juſt</hi> Recompence of their <hi>Errour,</hi> that would thus make void <hi>the Commandments of God through their vain Traditions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By what is ſaid, it is evident enough, that there is nothing ſo <hi>Unchriſtian,</hi> nothing ſo <hi>Unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable,</hi> as for Subjects to <hi>ſeek</hi> Occaſions to <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute</hi> the <hi>Wills</hi> and <hi>Pleaſures</hi> of their <hi>Princes;</hi> and how much more, to raiſe <hi>Tumults</hi> and <hi>levy Arms</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:49456:15"/> againſt them? Yea, though they were <hi>Heathens,</hi> and <hi>Tyrants,</hi> and the <hi>moſt profeſſed Enemies that can be imagined to God</hi> and <hi>Goodneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is nothing ſo great a <hi>Contradiction</hi> to <hi>right Reaſon,</hi> and the <hi>Spirit</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> as is the Spirit of a <hi>Rebel</hi> and a <hi>Traytor</hi> to his <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Country.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the Spirit of the Goſpel more eſpecially, it is a Spirit of <hi>Love, and Joy, and Peace, and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, and Long-ſuffering and Gentleneſs towards them,</hi> even towards the <hi>froward</hi> and <hi>unkind;</hi> how much more towards thoſe that are <hi>Gentle</hi> and <hi>Good.</hi> And therefore, there needeth no other Light to ſet off the <hi>Foulneſs</hi> of that <hi>Spirit</hi> that <hi>ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in the hearts</hi> of the <hi>Now Rebels</hi> in <hi>Arms</hi> againſt our preſent <hi>moſt Gracious <hi rend="blackletterType">and Liege Lord and Sovereign, King</hi>
               </hi> JAMES <hi rend="blackletterType">the Second;</hi> than to deſcribe to you the <hi>true</hi> Spirit of the <hi>Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel,</hi> as it was recommended by our <hi>Saviour</hi> unto his <hi>Diſciples</hi> and <hi>Followers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But becauſe the <hi>Now</hi> Rebels, to colour their moſt <hi>horrid Treaſon</hi> againſt their <hi>Lawful Sovereign,</hi> have endeavour'd to <hi>poyſon</hi> the minds of their <hi>Followers,</hi> where they come, with I know not what <hi>dark</hi> and <hi>damnable Inſinuations</hi> againſt <hi rend="blackletterType">A Prince ſo every way Great and Juſt and Good;</hi> I ſhall humbly crave leave, upon <hi>this</hi> Occaſion, and before the <hi>Common Souldiery here aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled,</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:49456:15"/> to expoſe the <hi>Monſtroſity</hi> of the <hi>now Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors treaſonable pretenſions and practiſings:</hi> and I ſhall expoſe it by the <hi>Sun-beam</hi> Light of his Majeſty's <hi>Undoubted Right</hi> of <hi>Blood</hi> to the <hi>Crown,</hi> and of his <hi>Unparallell'd Merits,</hi> and his <hi>Intereſts</hi> to <hi>defend</hi> that <hi>Right,</hi> againſt all <hi>Treaſons</hi> and Traiterous <hi>Conspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racies</hi> whatever: <hi>And,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, I ſhall crave leave to ſpeak a few words with <hi>Reverence,</hi> concerning his <hi rend="blackletterType">moſt Gracious Majeſty's moſt undoubted Right of Blood,</hi> &amp;c. It may ſeem needleſs to have his Majeſty's <hi>Titles</hi> after <hi>Proclamation</hi> to be declared, eſpecially in the <hi>Pulpit:</hi> Yet, give me leave, in <hi>Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance</hi> of the <hi>BLACK BOX,</hi> and the <hi>Excluding Bill</hi> more <hi>Black than That,</hi> and that ſtill more <hi>Black</hi> and <hi rend="blackletterType">Bloody <hi>Aſſociation</hi>
               </hi> that follow'd it, and which ſtill <hi>worketh in the Hearts of the Children of Diſobedience;</hi> to put you, eſpecially of the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Souldiery,</hi> in Remembrance;</p>
            <p>That our now Sovereign Lord <hi rend="blackletterType">King</hi> JAMES <hi rend="blackletterType">the Second,</hi> is the now <hi>only</hi> ſurvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving <hi>Son</hi> of King CHARLES <hi rend="blackletterType">the Martyr,</hi> Grandſon of King <hi rend="blackletterType">James</hi> that was of <hi>Scotland</hi> the <hi>Sixth of that Name,</hi> and of <hi>Great Britain</hi> the <hi>First:</hi> who was <hi>lawfully</hi> deſcended, both by Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Mothers ſide from King HENRY <hi rend="blackletterType">the Seventh,</hi> and the <hi rend="blackletterType">Great</hi> ELIZABETH, <hi rend="blackletterType">Daughter and Heir of</hi> Lionel <hi rend="blackletterType">Duke of</hi> Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:49456:16"/> 
               <hi rend="blackletterType">third Son to</hi> Edward <hi rend="blackletterType">the Third: Which King</hi> Henry <hi rend="blackletterType">the Seventh <hi>entailed the <hi rend="blackletterType">Crown</hi> of</hi>
               </hi> England <hi>by</hi> Act of Parliament <hi>upon the Iſſue of His, and his Queens Body <hi rend="blackletterType">Lawfully</hi> begotten.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No <hi>Prince</hi> ever mounted the <hi>Throne</hi> of <hi>England</hi> with a <hi>Title</hi> more <hi>undoubtedly</hi> apparent and clear! Clear as the <hi>Sun</hi> in its <hi>brightest</hi> Meridian! Clear as the <hi>Late King</hi> could make it, in a <hi>Declaration</hi> written with his own hand, to prevent the <hi>now Rebels</hi> pretenſions, and to prevent and avoid <hi>any Disputes</hi> for time to come, concerning his <hi>Now</hi> Majeſty's <hi>Succeſſion</hi> to the <hi rend="blackletterType">Crown!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>His late Majeſty's own Words to this purpoſe are publiſhed by the truly Loyal and Judicious Authour of the Addreſs to the</hi> Freemen <hi>and</hi> Freeholders <hi>of the Nation.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid.</hi> part <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. p. 14, 15, 16, 17,</note> But</p>
            <p>Secondly, Had not his Majeſty been <hi>born</hi> to be a <hi>King,</hi> I think there are but few that have the Honour to know him, who do not think him the <hi>Worthieſt</hi> Perſon to have been <hi>choſen</hi> our <hi>King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For, if ever we had a Prince that came to the Crown in the full <hi>Ripeneſs</hi> and <hi>Maturity</hi> as well of <hi rend="blackletterType">Royal Uertues</hi> as <hi rend="blackletterType">Years;</hi> one who brought to the <hi>Government</hi> of his people all that <hi>Experience,</hi> which others are a long time at much <hi>charge,</hi> and more <hi>hazard</hi> to learn; it is our preſent <hi rend="blackletterType">moſt Gracious Sovereign King</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:49456:16"/> JAMES: A <hi rend="blackletterType">Prince!</hi> whoſe <hi rend="blackletterType">Wiſdom, Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and Mercy</hi> (if men will be but ſo merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to themſelves as to do any thing that may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve it) A <hi rend="blackletterType">Prince!</hi> whoſe <hi rend="blackletterType">Munificence</hi> and <hi rend="blackletterType">Magnanimity,</hi> whoſe <hi rend="blackletterType">Sobriety</hi> and <hi rend="blackletterType">Tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance,</hi> whoſe <hi rend="blackletterType">Courage</hi> to dare <hi>bravely</hi> in the <hi>greateſt</hi> dangers, <hi>equal</hi> to his <hi rend="blackletterType">Chriſtian Fortitude</hi> in bearing the worſt of Evils from the hands of a ſort of <hi>Men-Devils</hi> among us: A <hi rend="blackletterType">Prince!</hi> whoſe <hi>firm <hi>
                     <hi rend="blackletterType">Fidelity</hi>
                  </hi>
               </hi> to his <hi>Friends,</hi> and whoſe <hi rend="blackletterType">Zeal</hi> for the <hi rend="blackletterType">Honour</hi> of the <hi rend="blackletterType">Engliſh Name and Nation</hi> are ſo <hi>notoriouſly</hi> known both at <hi>home</hi> and <hi>abroad,</hi> that even <hi>baſe Envy</hi> and <hi>Detraction</hi> have but render'd them the more <hi>acknowledged,</hi> and <hi rend="blackletterType">Jlluſtriouſly Conſpicuous.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All theſe ſhine by their <hi>Own Light,</hi> and need not my <hi>dim Taper</hi> to ſhew them by.</p>
            <p>But there is one Qualification which will <hi>gild</hi> and <hi>adorn</hi> his <hi>Crown,</hi> and add a <hi rend="blackletterType">Luſtre</hi> to his <hi rend="blackletterType">Great Name</hi> in <hi>Chronicle,</hi> and that is, his <hi rend="blackletterType">Uera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city;</hi> And <hi>King JAMES the Second</hi> ſhall be known in the Ages to come by this <hi rend="blackletterType">Appellative, of King</hi> JAMES <hi rend="blackletterType">the Juſt, Prince of his Word.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Go to then, all they that whine and fear for their <hi>Religion,</hi> their <hi>Religion!</hi> bluſh they, and let them all be aſhamed and confounded, becauſe of the <hi>Evils</hi> which they <hi>fear,</hi> only becauſe they are
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:49456:17"/> 
               <hi>not.</hi> Have we not for our <hi>Security,</hi> as a <hi>Pawn,</hi> the <hi>Word</hi> of a <hi>Prince,</hi> who <hi>never</hi> yet <hi>broke</hi> his Word?</p>
            <p>But if neither his <hi>Royal</hi> Title, nor his <hi>Royal</hi> Merits may prevail with <hi>raſh</hi> and <hi>unadviſed</hi> Men to work them up to <hi>Obedience,</hi> let it be conſider'd, in the</p>
            <p>Third place, of what value his <hi>Intereſts</hi> are, to <hi>ſecure</hi> and <hi>defend</hi> the Rights both of his <hi>Title</hi> and his <hi>Merits.</hi> For though his Majeſty hold all by <hi>Love</hi> (all his <hi>Kingdoms</hi> and <hi>Countries</hi> having long ſince <hi>received</hi> him into their <hi>Hearts)</hi> yet I ſhall here ſubjoin, to the <hi>Honour</hi> of his <hi>Majesty,</hi> the <hi>Comfort</hi> of his <hi>Friends,</hi> and the <hi>Terrour</hi> of his <hi>Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies,</hi> theſe two Conſiderations:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> That his <hi>Majesty</hi> hath the undoubted <hi>Forces</hi> of <hi>England, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his <hi>Dominions</hi> and <hi>Countries</hi> in his own power, and at his <hi>ſole</hi> Command. And the <hi>Numerous</hi> and <hi>very Loyal Addreſſes</hi> that have been ſent from <hi>all</hi> the <hi>Quarters</hi> of theſe his Kingdoms, are ſo highly expreſſive of a <hi>Godly Emulation</hi> in all his <hi>Loyal</hi> Subjects to ſerve him, that it hath hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto ſeem'd the <hi>only</hi> Conteſt within the three Kingdoms, who ſhould be the <hi>forwardeſt</hi> in <hi>Duty</hi> to <hi>vow their Lives and Eſtates</hi> a <hi>Sacrifice</hi> in defence of his <hi>Imperial Highneſs</hi> and the <hi rend="blackletterType">Prerogative.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What ſhould I ſpeak of his <hi rend="blackletterType">Militia?</hi> of his
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:49456:17"/> 
               <hi rend="blackletterType">Magazines,</hi> and his <hi rend="blackletterType">Naval</hi> Forces at Sea, and of his <hi rend="blackletterType">moſt Wiſe Council?</hi> What of the <hi rend="blackletterType">Thrice happy</hi> Agreement which hath been all along, and ſtill is, and which we beſeech Almighty God to continue between him and his <hi>most Loyal Parliament?</hi> Conſider we,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> His <hi>Friends</hi> and <hi>Alliances</hi> abroad, and their mighty <hi>Puiſſance</hi> to aſſert his <hi>Right:</hi> They are all of them of ſuch <hi>Invincible</hi> ſtrength and might both by <hi>Sea</hi> and <hi>Land,</hi> as by God's conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing to <hi>bleſs</hi> the <hi>Union</hi> will give no Cauſe to fear either the growing <hi>Factions</hi> at <hi>home,</hi> or the growing <hi>Greatneſs</hi> (ſhall I call it?) of our <hi>Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour-Nation.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Nunc Cauſa valens causàmque tuentibus Armis.</q>
            <p>And therefore as the King doth, no doubt, out of a moſt Religious and Godly heart, ſo let us lift up our <hi>Hands</hi> and our <hi>Eyes</hi> to God on <hi>High,</hi> and let us from the <hi>bottom</hi> of our <hi>Hearts</hi> beſeech him to keep and defend <hi rend="blackletterType">His own King,</hi> whom (maugre all the <hi>Evil Deſigns</hi> of <hi>Evil Men</hi> among us) he hath ſet on the Throne of the Engliſh Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for the Glory of his Name, and for the comfort of us his Subjects. Let us pray for him, and againſt his Enemies, <hi>That God would abate their Pride, and aſſwage their Malice, and diſcover
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:49456:18"/> daily more and more, and confound their Devices.</hi> And to our Prayers, let us each man in his Station, <hi>manfully</hi> endeavour <hi>his Peace,</hi> and our <hi>own</hi> in <hi>His.</hi> And to this End, let all <hi>Murmurings</hi> and <hi>Repinings</hi> and <hi>Diſcontents</hi> towards the <hi>Government</hi> for ever ceaſe from amongſt us. <hi>Let us follow Peace, and the things that make for Peace, and the things in which we may Edifie one another;</hi> quietly ſubmitting our ſelves to the <hi>Government</hi> that God hath ſet <hi>over</hi> us, and bleſſing God that he hath account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed us <hi>worthy</hi> of ſo <hi rend="blackletterType">Good a Prince</hi> to <hi>Rule</hi> and to <hi>Reign</hi> over us, and beſeeching him to <hi>continue</hi> his Reign <hi>long</hi> and <hi>prosperous;</hi> even for <hi>Many</hi> and for <hi>Many</hi> Years! And to this <hi>Good Prayer,</hi> let eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one here preſent be concern'd to ſay, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:49456:18"/>
            <head>A Catalogue of ſome Books Printed for, and Sold by <hi>Luke Meredith,</hi> at the <hi>King's Head,</hi> at the West End of St. <hi>Paul's Church-yard.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>AN Introduction to the <hi>Old Engliſh Hiſtory;</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended in Three ſeveral Tracts: The <hi>Firſt,</hi> An Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Petyt's Rights of the Commons Aſſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed;</hi> and to a Book, Entituled; <hi>Jani Anglorum Facies No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>va:</hi> The Second Edition very much enlarged. The <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond,</hi> An <hi>Anſwer</hi> to a Book, Entituled, <hi>Argumentum An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinormanicum;</hi> much upon the ſame Subject: Never be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Publiſhed. The <hi>Third,</hi> The Exact Hiſtory of the <hi>Succeſſion</hi> of the <hi>Crown</hi> of <hi>England:</hi> The Second Edition, alſo very much enlarged. Together, with an <hi>Appendix,</hi> containing ſeveral Records, and a Series of <hi>Great Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils</hi> and <hi>Parliaments,</hi> Before and After the <hi>Conqueſt,</hi> unto the End of the Reign of <hi>Henry</hi> the Third. And a <hi>Gloſſary,</hi> expounding many Words, uſed frequently in our Antient Records, Laws, and Hiſtorians. Publiſhed for the <hi>Vindication</hi> of <hi>Truth,</hi> and the <hi>Aſſiſtance</hi> of ſuch as deſire with Satisfaction to read, and truly underſtand the Antient <hi>Engliſh Historians,</hi> and other Pieces of <hi>Antiquity.</hi> By <hi>Robert Brady,</hi> Doctor in Phyſick.</p>
            <p>Two Treatiſes: The <hi>Firſt,</hi> Concerning <hi>Reproaching</hi> and <hi>Cenſure;</hi> The <hi>Second,</hi> An <hi>Anſwer</hi> to Mr. <hi>Serjeant's Sure-Footing.</hi> To which are annexed, <hi>Three Sermons</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:49456:19"/> Preached upon ſeveral Occaſions; and very uſeful for theſe Times. By the late Learned and Reverend <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Falkner,</hi> D. D.</p>
            <p>A Dialogue between a <hi>Paſtor,</hi> and his <hi>Pariſhioner,</hi> touching the <hi>Lord's Supper:</hi> Wherein the moſt material Doubts and Scruples about Receiving that Holy <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> are removed, and the Way thereto diſcovered to be both plain and pleaſant. Very uſeful for Private Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians in theſe Scrupulous Times. By <hi>Michael Altham.</hi> The <hi>Second Edition.</hi> To which are added, Some ſhort Prayers, fitted for that Occaſion; and a Morning and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vening Prayer, for the Uſe of Private Families.</p>
            <p>Sober and Serious Conſiderations: Occaſioned by the Death of His Moſt Sacred MAJESTY, King <hi>Charles</hi> II. (of ever Bleſſed Memory,) And the Serious Time of <hi>LENT,</hi> following it. Together with a Brief Hiſtorical Account of the Firſt Riſe, Progreſs, and Encreaſe of <hi>Phanaticiſm,</hi> in <hi>England;</hi> and the Fatal Conſequents thereof. Now made Publick, in tendency to the Peace of the Kingdom. By a <hi>Gentleman</hi> in Communion with the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as now by Law Eſtabliſh'd.</p>
            <p>The Songs of <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Deborah</hi> Paraphras'd; with <hi>Poems</hi> on ſeveral Occaſions. Never before Publiſhed. To which is added, A <hi>Pindarick</hi> on Sir <hi>Roger L' Eſtrange.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>The End of the Catalogue.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:49456:19"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
